In this update,
この話では パンデミック中
we窶决e going to talk about how we can make
どのように時間を
有効に使えるかを考えます
good use of our time
during the pandemic.
まず 幾らかの情報を
お伝えします
But first, we窶囘 like to share a few updates.
We窶决e sad to report that, as of December 10,
残念なことですが
12月10日までに
we have lost 25,658
2万5658人の兄弟姉妹が
新型コロナウイルスで亡くなりました
brothers and sisters to COVID-19.
Our prayers are certainly with all
大切な人を亡くした皆さんのために
心から祈っています
who have lost loved ones.
最近 新しいオミクロン株のことが
大々的に報じられています
Recently, the new Omicron variant
has received a lot of news coverage.
現時点では分からないことが
たくさんあります
At this point, there are still many unknowns.
Brothers and sisters, we don窶冲 need to panic.
でも兄弟姉妹
動揺する必要はありません
Keep following the same basic precautions
that have worked well:
これまでと同じように
基本的な予防を続けてください
wearing masks,
マスクを着け
フィジカル･ディスタンスを保ち
physical distancing,
frequently washing our hands,
頻繁に手を洗い 可能なら
ワクチンを受けてください
and getting vaccinated, if possible.
「2021 統治体からの話（7）」で
レッシュ兄弟は
In the 2021 Governing Body Update #7,
Brother Lﾃｶsch mentioned that over 80 percent
世界中のべテル家族の
80パーセント以上が
of the worldwide Bethel family
was vaccinated.
ワクチンを接種したと言っていました
We are glad to inform you
that now over 99 percent
うれしいことに 今では
世界中のべテル家族の
99パーセント以上が
of our worldwide Bethel family is vaccinated,
ワクチン接種を終えています
and so are over 95 percent of our
また 野外の特別全時間奉仕者の
95パーセント以上が
special full-time servants in the field.
接種を終えました
ワクチンを接種したことは
Many of our brothers and sisters have had
多くの兄弟姉妹にとって
良い結果になっています
good results from being vaccinated.
For example,
例えば ブルガリアのある地域では
地元の聖職者が
in some parts of Bulgaria,
the local clergy say that vaccines
ワクチンは「悪魔からの毒だ」
と言っています
are 窶徘oison from the Devil.窶 Dialogue: 0,0:01:52.13,0:01:54.57,Default,,0,0,0,,So there is much pressure in the community
人々はワクチンを接種しないように
という強い圧力を受けています
not {
Despite this, one sister and her husband
そのような中 ある姉妹とご主人は
統治体からの話を視聴し
watched the Governing Body updates
and made their personal decision
to get vaccinated.
よく考えた上で ワクチンを
接種することにしました
その後 姉妹は
雇い主から電話を受け
Later, the sister’s employer called her
and said that in order
to comply with government regulations,
政府の決まりでワクチンを
接種していない人は
she couldn’t return to work
if she had not been vaccinated.
職場に戻れないことになった
と言われました
姉妹がワクチン接種を
終えていることを伝えると
How surprised the manager was to learn
that the sister was already vaccinated!
雇い主はびっくりしました
In fact,
実は その職場でワクチンを
受けていたのは姉妹だけでした
she was the only employee who was vaccinated.
Everyone else had to be laid off.
他の人は全員解雇されました
The manager asked our sister
雇い主は 解雇された人たちの
穴埋めをするため
if she had any vaccinated friends
who could replace
姉妹にワクチン接種を終えた友達が
いないか尋ねました
the employees who had been fired.
The manager then called other Witnesses
雇い主は姉妹から紹介された
兄弟姉妹に電話し
that she knew to see if they had any
接種を終えた人で仕事を
探している人がいないか尋ねました
vaccinated friends who needed employment.
That evening,
その晩 ほぼ全ての求人枠が
埋まりました
nearly all the positions were filled.
The head of staff asked our sisters,
責任者は姉妹たちにこう聞きました
「接種を終えた女性をどうして
そんなにたくさん知ってるの？」
“How do you know so many vaccinated women?”
姉妹たちは自分たちの
見方について話せました
A fine witness was given.
In the end, 14 sisters
結局14人の姉妹と
and 1 Bible student were employed
聖書を学んでいる1人の人が
採用されました
because they followed
the good guidance and Bible principles
これまでの統治体の話に
含まれていた
役立つアドバイスや 聖書の原則を
当てはめていたからです
that have been shared
in our various Governing Body updates.
では パンデミック中
Now, let’s get back to our topic
of putting our time to good use
時間を有効に使うことについて
考えましょう
during the pandemic.
多くの皆さんが開拓奉仕を始めたり
聖書をさらに深く学んだり
It’s been exciting to hear how many of you
have reached out to pioneer,
started new study projects,
電話伝道や手紙伝道のスキルを
磨いたりしていることを聞いて
and refined your telephone
and letter-writing skills.
励まされています
That is time well spent.
時間をよく活用しておられます
今回の話では さらに2つ
In this month’s update,
we will discuss two additional ways
時間をどのように
賢く使えるかを考えます
we can use our time wisely:
helping inactive ones
不活発な人を助けることと
and improving our reading and writing skills.
読み書きのスキルを
向上させることです
It has been wonderful to see so many
of our brothers and sisters
パンデミック中 不活発だった
非常に多くの兄弟姉妹が
who were inactive begin associating
クリスチャンの活動を再開したのは
本当にうれしいことです
with us again during the pandemic.
あなたもその1人ですか
If that describes you,
please know
もしそうなら 統治体は
本当にうれしく思っています
that the Governing Body
warmly welcomes you back!
お帰りなさい
Imagine the joy that Jehovah, Jesus,
and all the angels
エホバも イエスも 天使たちも
あなたが戻ってきたのを見て
喜んでいるに違いありません
in heaven have experienced
at seeing you return.
まだ戻ってきていない人は
どうしているのでしょうか
But what about those
who have not yet returned?
次の詩編作者のように
感じているかもしれません
They might feel like the psalmist,
as recorded
at Psalm 119:176.
詩編 119:176です
こうあります
There we read:
“I have strayed like a lost sheep.
「私は迷い出た羊のように
さまよっている
“Search for your servant,
私を捜してください
for I have not forgotten your commandments.”
私はあなたのおきてを
忘れていない」
Right now, some inactive ones
may be praying to Jehovah,
不活発な人たちの中には
エホバにこう祈っている人が
いるかもしれません
saying: ‘Search for me.
「私を捜してください
戻れるよう助けてください」
I need help to come back.’
その人たちはエホバを
忘れたわけではありませんが
They haven’t forgotten Jehovah,
but for various reasons,
さまざまな理由で
自分だけで戻ることができていません
they haven’t been able
to come back on their own.
エホバはどう感じているでしょうか
How does Jehovah feel about such ones?
エゼキエル 34:15,16には
こうあります
Ezekiel 34:15, 16 says:
“I myself will feed my sheep . . .
「私は自ら自分の羊を養［う］
“The lost one I will search for,
いなくなった羊を捜し
はぐれた羊を連れ戻し
“the stray I will bring back,
“the injured I will bandage,
けがをした羊に包帯をし
弱い羊を力づける」
and the weak I will strengthen.”
Can Jehovah use you to find his lost sheep?
エホバは皆さんを用いて
いなくなった羊を見つけることが
できますか
Absolutely!
もちろんです
Many of you have
reached out to inactive ones.
すでに多くの兄弟姉妹が
努力しています
In the following video,
次のビデオをご覧ください
notice how publishers took the initiative
不活発な人が
エホバのもとに戻れるよう
to help others return to Jehovah.
兄弟姉妹はどのように
援助しているでしょうか
兄がエホバのもとに
戻ってくるかどうか
I didn’t know what my brother was ever
going to do about the truth.
分かりませんでした
10代の頃は伝道もしていました
As a teenager, he was a publisher
in the congregation.
でも残念なことに
16歳の頃家を出て
By the time he was 16,
sadly, he decided to leave home,
エホバに仕えるのを
やめてしまいました
and then he no longer served Jehovah.
But then, when we came back
to Seattle and settled down,
妻と私はシアトルに戻ってきたので
兄とよく連絡を取るようになりました
then we had more contact with him.
My wife and I
had been providing meals for him
兄の妻が脳腫瘍だったので
兄に食事を届けていました
because his wife had a brain tumor.
But the beautiful thing
is that our congregation
会衆の兄弟姉妹も 親切に食事を
届けてくれるようになりました
started taking him meals.
When my brother’s wife was hospitalized,
時には 兄の妻が入院している
病院に行って
they even assisted at the hospital
兄を励ましてくれることもありました
to visit him and give him encouragement.
That had a big impact upon him.
兄は 兄弟姉妹の愛や親切に
心を打たれました
He could see the closeness
of the congregation,
それがきっかけで エホバのもとに
戻りたいと思ったようです
and I think that built a desire
that he would really like to do more.
When my brother went to the Kingdom Hall,
he was only able to do that
その後 王国会館に
行くようになりました
for two weeks
and then COVID-19 struck.
ところが2週間後に
パンデミックが始まりました
But an elder talked to him the first time
he went to the Kingdom Hall,
でも初めて
王国会館に行った時
1人の長老と電話番号を
交換していました
and they exchanged phone numbers.
And so they were able to communicate.
その長老が兄と連絡を取り
Zoomを使えるようにしてくれたので
And that elder helped set him up on Zoom,
and he was able to attend the meetings then.
全ての集会に出席するようになりました
And he went to all the meetings.
Then I encouraged him
to have a personal study,
それで私が
聖書を学んでみるよう勧めると
and he said, “Well I’m doing my study.”
「もうやってるよ」と言いました
私は誰かと一緒に
聖書レッスンをすることについて
Of all things, it was a terminology issue.
He didn’t know about having
a personal Bible study with someone.
言っていたんですが
意味がよく分からなかったようです
He had some more encouragement
from a family friend
兄が集会に出席している
ことを知った友達も
that found out
that he was coming to meetings,
いろいろ励ましてくれました
and then he started to have
his own Bible study.
その後聖書レッスンを始め
よく進歩するようになりました
And that’s when he really started
to make progress.
59年かかりました
It took 59 years!
I had the privilege of actually performing
the baptism for my own brother.
うれしいことに 私が兄に
バプテスマを施すことが
できました
パンデミックが始まってすぐに
伝道の方法を
At the beginning of the pandemic,
we knew that our ministry
変えなければならないことが
分かりました
was going to change.
And so we thought about what to do,
何ができるかいろいろ考えて
and we came up with this little project,
これまで奉仕した会衆の
不活発な人たちのことを思い出して
making a list of all the inactive people
that we could think of that we’d been
with in other congregations
リストを作ることにしました
その中には 若い人も
たくさん含まれています
—lots of young people and others.
40人ぐらいの人をリストアップ
することができました
And when we did that list,
there were about 40 people on that list.
So we’ve emailed, we’ve called,
その人たちにメールしたり
電話したりしました
we’ve texted,
and we’ve written lots of letters.
手紙もたくさん書きました
Some of them, we haven’t heard anything from,
中には返事がない人もいましたが
連絡してこないで という人は
一人もいませんでした
but nobody has rejected our efforts.
I contacted one man
ある男性に連絡しました
40年近く前に会った人です
whom I had met almost 40 years ago
when I was 19 years old.
私が19歳の頃です
We reestablished contact.
その人はZoomの集会に
出席するようになり
He began to attend all the meetings on Zoom,
「いつまでも幸せに暮らせます」で
一緒に聖書を勉強しています
and now we’re studying the Bible
in the Enjoy Life Forever! {
長年不活発だった兄弟とも
連絡を取りました
We contacted one brother
who’d been inactive for many years.
Now he attends all the meetings on Zoom.
今はZoomの集会に出席しています
He has been reactivated,
兄弟は重い病気を抱えていますが
再び活発に奉仕するようになりました
and all of this despite
some very serious health problems.
Patience and persistence are required
不活発な人を助けるには
辛抱強さと 諦めないことが大切です
when reaching out to these dear ones.
We love them, and so we contact
みんなのことを愛しているので
毎週何人かに連絡しています
some on that list every week.
本当にうれしく感じています
We’re so happy.
連絡した人のうち3人は
今定期的に集会に出席しています
Three of the persons that we’ve contacted
are now regularly attending the meetings.
Two of them are studying the Bible.
2人は聖書レッスンもしています
愛する兄弟姉妹が
エホバのもとに戻ってくるのを見て
It’s really been encouraging
for us to see these ones
that we love so much return to Jehovah.
本当に励まされています
これからも エホバに引き寄せられて
戻ってくる人がいると思います
And really, if Jehovah is drawing them,
they’re going to respond.
I’m sure you agree
エホバは確かに
迷い出た羊を助ける
私たちの努力を祝福しています
that Jehovah blessed these efforts
to reach out to his lost sheep.
What a wonderful way to use our time
パンデミック中 時間を有効に使う
素晴らしい方法です
during the pandemic!
最近 米国の巡回監督から
受け取った報告によると
One circuit overseer in the United States
recently reported that 76 individuals
巡回区内の76人が活発に
奉仕するようになったようです
in his circuit have been reactivated.
That’s the equivalent
of an entire congregation!
1つの会衆ができるくらいの
人数です
エホバに祈り
We encourage you
to prayerfully think of inactive ones
自分が知っている不活発な人について
考えてみてください
that you might know.
家族や友達の中に
不活発な人がいますか
It could be a family member or friend.
Can you give them a call
電話をかけたり 手紙を書いたり
メールを送ったりできますか
or send them a letter or a text message?
And if they respond and attend a meeting,
良い反応があって
集会に来てくれるなら
make them feel welcome.
温かく歓迎しましょう
We hope that many more lost sheep
終わりが来る前に
さらに多くの人がエホバのもとに
戻ってくることを願っています
will return to Jehovah before the end.
2つ目の方法は
Another good use of our time
読み書きのスキルを
向上させることです
is improving our reading and writing skills.
Reading and writing
いつの時代も エホバの民にとって
読み書きは大切です
has always been important
for Jehovah’s people.
ご存じのように
Remember, the kings of Israel were told
イスラエルの王たちは
「［律法を］書き写し」
to “write [out] . . . a copy of [the] Law”
and “read from it
all the days of [their] life.”
「生涯ずっと読［む］」ように
言われていました
Jesus was raised by a poor family,
イエスは貧しい家庭で育ちましたが
読むことができました
yet he was able to read.
We remember the time when he went
into the synagogue in Nazareth.
イエスがナザレの会堂でしたことを
覚えていますか
He was able to open the Isaiah scroll
イザヤの巻物を開きました
今のように章や節はありません
—which had no chapters and verses—
and locate and read the correct scripture.
でも 聖句を探して
読むことができました
パウロがテモテに言ったことも
覚えておきましょう
And let’s not forget what Paul told Timothy.
Timothy was already an elder.
すでに長老だったテモテに
パウロは何と言いましたか
Yet, Paul said to him:
“Continue applying yourself
to public reading.”
「朗読⋯⋯に励んでください」
と言いました
このように 聖書は読むことの
大切さを強調しています
So in view
of the Bible’s emphasis on reading,
it is not surprising that God’s organization
ですから神の組織は長年
人々に読み書きを教えてきました
has a wonderful history of helping people
all over the world to learn to read.
世界各地で
そうした活動をしてきました
Over the past 70 years,
これまで70年 エホバの証人は
世界中で大勢の人々に
Jehovah’s Witnesses have taught
thousands of people worldwide
to read and write.
読み書きを教えてきたのです
For example, in Mexico,
例えば メキシコでは
we have helped more than 156,000 people
15万6000人以上の人に
読み書きを教えてきました
to learn to read and write.
幾つかの国では
そうした活動が表彰されました
We’ve received awards
in several countries for our efforts.
今はどうですか
What about today?
It’s true that now in many languages
最近ではテクノロジーのおかげで
出版物の内容を耳で聞けるように
なっています
we have technology that enables us
to listen to our publications.
But we don’t want to be content to rely
でも私たちは
オーディオ版の出版物だけに
頼りたいとは思いません
on audio publications alone.
自分で聖書を読み 学べるように
なりたいと思っています
We want to be able to read
and to study the Bible for ourselves
and to dig into the wonderful information
「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」から
与えられる情報も
provided by “the faithful
and discreet slave.”
熟考したいと思っています
読めるようになることには
ほかにもどんな利点があるでしょうか
What are some other benefits that come
from learning to read well?
A new article was recently published
最近jw.orgに 新しい記事が
アップされました
on jw.org entitled
“Why Reading Is Important for Children.”
「本を読むことはとても大切」
という記事です
これは特に 親の皆さんのために
用意されました
This was prepared
with you dear parents in mind.
But, really, reading is something
でも読むことは 私たち全てにとって
とても大切です
that all{
Why?
なぜですか
その記事にある通り
読むと 想像力が身に付きます
The article explained that reading
stirs the imagination.
It builds character
心が豊かになります
問題について考える力も
身に付きます
and helps us to reason on our problems.
It helps us develop qualities
such as patience,
我慢したり 自分を制したりする力や
共感力も身に付きます
self-control, and empathy.
読むと 深く考える力も身に付きます
And reading promotes deep thinking.
パンデミック中 兄弟姉妹の中には
時間を活用して
During the pandemic,
some of our brothers have been making
good use of their time
読み書きを学んでいる人もいます
by learning to read and write.
Let’s hear how they have benefited.
どんな良い結果が
見られているでしょうか
When the coronavirus broke out
感染症が国中に広がったので
学校は閉鎖され
throughout the country, schools were shut down
and many parents either couldn’t go to work
多くの親は自宅待機か
テレワークになりました
or they had to work from home.
One circuit overseer set a goal
ある巡回監督は 巡回区内の親たちに
この機会を活用して
to encourage the parents in his circuit
to take advantage of the opportunity
子供たちに
読み書きを教えるよう励ましました
to carry on teaching
their children to read and write
with the objective of assisting them
to become publishers.
伝道者になるよう助けるためです
多くの親がその励ましに応じ
37人の子供たちが
Many parents responded
to the encouragement, and this resulted
in 37 young ones becoming proficient
in reading and writing.
上手に読み書きが
できるようになりました
A sister named Sara
サラという姉妹は
時間を取って読み書きを
勉強したいと思っていました
had been trying for some time to learn
to read and write.
長老である夫は妻を助けたいと
思っていましたが
At home, her husband tried to help her,
but they just couldn’t find enough time
毎日忙しく
多くの責任があったので
because of their day-to-day activities
and many responsibilities.
なかなか時間が取れませんでした
Now, when the pandemic
でもパンデミックで
いろいろな活動ができなくなったので
limited their activities,
her husband, who is an elder,
夫は空いた時間を
活用することにしました
took advantage of the extra time.
He began to help her
週に何度か 妻に読み方を
教えることにしたんです
several times a week to learn to read.
Now she has the joy
姉妹は聖書や他の出版物を
自分で読めるようになり
of reading the Bible
and other publications on her own.
喜んでいます
王国の歌を歌うのも大好きです
She also loves to sing the Kingdom songs
自分の歌の本を使って
歌っています
using her own songbook.
コンフォートという女性は
One Bible student named Comfort
聖書を学んでいましたが
字が読めませんでした
earnestly longed
to be able to read the Bible.
She became downhearted
when the pandemic began
聖書を読めるようになりたいと思い
識字クラスに行っていましたが
and wondered who was going
to help her read now
パンデミックでクラスに
行けなくなったので
that she couldn’t physically attend
a literacy class.
がっかりしていました
A local congregation elder gave her
some excellent practical suggestions,
それで会衆の長老が
自分で勉強を続けるように励まし
and he encouraged her
to continue practicing on her own.
幾つか役立つアドバイスをしました
With determination and persistence,
コンフォートはアドバイスを当てはめ
諦めずに頑張り続けました
Comfort applied the suggestions.
She made steady progress,
and she now reads well.
今では上手に読むことができます
She conducts five Bible studies.
聖書レッスンも5件行っています
She is also assisting
her own 14-year-old daughter
また 14歳の娘に
読み書きを教えています
to learn how to read and write.
2020年の「いつも喜びましょう！」
地区大会でバプテスマを受けました
Comfort was baptized
at the 2020 “Always Rejoice”!
Regional Convention.
ニカラグアで奉仕する
マリア姉妹は69歳です
Maria is our 69-year-old sister in Nicaragua,
and she’s been a regular pioneer
6年以上 正規開拓奉仕をしています
for over six years.
学校に通えなかったので
She never had formal schooling,
姉妹たちと聖書を勉強しながら
読み方を覚えました
and so she learned to read
as she studied the Bible with our sisters,
but she didn’t learn to write.
でも書くことはできませんでした
When the pandemic started,
Maria was very discouraged
パンデミックが始まり
姉妹はとてもがっかりしました
because she didn’t know
how to use her cell phone to preach,
携帯電話を使って伝道することも
手紙を書くこともできなかったからです
and she didn’t know how to write letters.
But some of her fellow pioneers
offered to help.
でも何人かの開拓者が助けました
一緒に伝道する人が
So Maria would dictate her words
to her field service partner
マリア姉妹の言ったことを
書き取って手紙にします
who would then write the letter.
そして その手紙の写真を撮って
マリア姉妹に送ります
Her field service partners
would send Maria photographs
of the letters they wrote in her behalf.
マリア姉妹はその写真を見ながら
自分で手紙を書きます
And using the photographs,
Maria would then copy them
so as to write her own letters.
このようにしてマリア姉妹は
だんだん文字が書けるようになりました
This helped Maria
to start developing writing skills.
今は自分で手紙を書くことが
できます
She now writes her own letters.
If you could see the letters that she writes,
ご覧のように とてもきれいな字です
what neat handwriting she’s learned
そして 自分が伝えたいことを
上手に書けるようになりました
to have, and how well she expresses herself!
エホバは姉妹を祝福しています
Obviously, she has Jehovah’s blessing,
私たちはみんな
姉妹の努力に励まされています
but it’s certainly an encouragement
to all of us to try to continue to improve.
本当に素晴らしい
時間の使い方ではないでしょうか
What a beautiful way to use
our time during the pandemic!
読み書きができないということは
But let’s not
—even for a minute—
think that literacy is an issue
決して世界のごく限られた場所だけの
問題ではありません
in only a few parts of the world.
実際 この問題は至る所で
見られます
Really, literacy
is an issue everywhere!
And, if we’re being honest with ourselves,
自分のことを正直に考えると
私たちのほとんどは
probably most of us would say
読み書きのスキルを向上させる必要が
あるのではないでしょうか
that we could improve
in our reading and writing.
So why not make the effort to do so?
では そのために努力するのは
いかがですか
統治体が最近
Note what the Governing Body said
全ての支部委員会に送った手紙には
こう書かれています
in a recent letter to all Branch Committees:
“We want our brothers and sisters
to progress spiritually
「私たちは 兄弟姉妹が
エホバとの絆を強め
“and grow to maturity.
十分に成長するよう願っています
“In large measure, this requires
that they be able to read
そのためには 神の言葉 聖書や
出版物を読んで
“and study God’s Word
along with our publications.
学べるようになる必要があります
“Many of the ways in which we serve God
クリスチャンの活動の多くには
読む能力が求められます
“involve the ability to read.
“For example,
例えば 全てのクリスチャンには
“all Christians have
the weighty responsibility
大切な真理を教えるという
重い責任があります
“of teaching vital truths to others.
読むスキルは
長老や援助奉仕者が
“And appointed men have many responsibilities
さまざまな責任を果たす際にも
役立ちます⋯⋯
“that involve reading. . . .
一般的に言って
“In general,
私たちクリスチャンは読む能力を
身に付ける必要があります」
Christians should be able to read.”
どうすれば読み方を学んだり
So how could we learn to read
or improve in our reading?
そのスキルを伸ばしたり
できるでしょうか
Here are two ways:
2つの方法があります
Ask a friend, a family member,
or someone in your congregation
友達や家族や会衆の兄弟姉妹に
助けてもらうことです
to help you.
また 「読み書きに励む」という
とても役立つ冊子もあります
An excellent tool
to assist is the Apply Yourself
to Reading and Writing{
現在 この冊子は123の言語で
入手できます
It is available in 123 languages.
入手方法は会衆の長老に
尋ねることができます
Why not ask your congregation elders
about how to obtain this brochure?
文字を知っていて単語も分かるなら
If you already know the alphabet
and you can recognize words,
audio recordings
of our literature may also help.
出版物のオーディオ版も
役立つかもしれません
As you listen to the recording,
オーディオを聞きながら
それに合わせて出版物を読みます
read along in the written publication.
Work to imitate the pronunciation
できるだけ同じように
発音してください
as you hear each word.
聞いた通りに言います
Improving our reading and writing
読み書きのスキルを磨くことは
パンデミック中
is a great way to use our time
during the pandemic!
時間を活用する
とても良い方法です
皆さんはこの大変な時期にも
エホバとの絆を強め
You brothers and sisters have shown
that you can thrive spiritually
and build others up
during a time of adversity.
仲間を励ますよう努力しています
You have made good use of your time.
時間を有効に使っています
May all of us continue to do so
では皆さん これからも
不活発な人たちを助けましょう
by assisting inactive ones
and by improving our reading skills.
また上手に読めるように
なりましょう
Be assured
統治体はいつも
皆さん全てのことを祈っています
that the Governing Body keeps
all of you in our prayers.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
JW Broadcasting®でした
this is JW Broadcasting®.